Finding Aid for The Bicentennial Dilemma: Who's in Control? Videorecordings, 1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bicentennial dilemma: who's in control? videorecordings 1975
Bicentennial Dilemma: Who's in Charge?
1 folders
19 videotapes
0566 Aa 1
Teach-in organized by University of Michigan students. Held from November 2-4, 1975, this three-day teach-in investigated the role of technology in corporate and government "control." Specific topics included: assassinations, corporate manipulation, subversion of the forces of dissent, police repression, surveillance and dataveillance, and mind control. DVD and streaming files from original EIAJ 1/2" open-reel videotapes of speakers at all sessions.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Provenance unknown
The collection is open to research. DVD use copies are available in the library. Streaming files are currently on-line for parts of some sessions; other can be mounted upon request to the library's reference staff.
The EIAJ (half-inch, open-reel) videotapes in the collection were digitized in 2009 as part of a library video preservation project. Preservation master beta tapes for all titles and high resolution digital files were created along with DVD and streaming files for all titles. The DVDs are available for use in the library. A selection of the streaming files may be available online at a given time, others can be mounted on request.
A group of University of Michigan students conceived of the teach-in "The Bicentennial Dilemma: Who's In Control?" in response to a television interview with Frank Church, "chairperson of the Senate Select Committee probing the Intelligence Community" in which he stated that "the Intelligence Network has the technological capacity to impose 'total tyranny' in the United States" (The Michigan Daily, October 31, 1975).
Held from November 2-4, 1975, this three-day teach-in (unaffiliated with the University of Michigan) included a series of speakers, workshops, panel discussions, and musical performances all investigating the role of technology in corporate and government "control." Specific topics included: assassinations, corporate manipulation, subversion of the forces of dissent, police repression, surveillance and "dataveillance," and mind control.
Twenty-nine speakers from all different sectors participated, including David DuBois of the Black Panther Party, Robert Katz from the Assassination Information Bureau, Chuck Morgan of the ACLU, Tim Butz a former intelligence agent, author Mark Lane. William Domhoff, Sidney Lens, Carl Oglesby, Maureen O'Rourke, William Kunstler, William Burrroughs, Beverly Moore, William Stirngfellow, Jeremy Rifkin and Eqbal Ahmad.
The collection consists of nineteen original recordings on 1/2-inch EIAJ reel-to-reel videotapes of the teach-in and one folder with teach-in schedules and outlines as well as handwritten notes taken during the sessions (writer unknown). In 2009 preservation and use copies of the tapes were made including a Beta SP preservation master, a DVD copy and a streaming file. The original tapes were in relatively good condition, though there are occasional problems with audio and video levels in the recordings and occasional tracking and dropout problems during dubbing. The derivatives were created on a one-to-one basis with the original.
Only a selection of the streaming files are currently on-line. Others can be mounted by sending a request the Bentley Historical Library reference staff (bentley.ref@umiclh.edu)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Assassination--United States--Congresses.; Brainwashing--United States--Congresses.; Political persecution--United States--Congresses.; Political corruption--United States--Congresses.
Contributors:
Ahmad, Eqbal.; Barnet, Richard J.; Borman, Nancy.; Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997; Butz, Tim.; Chorover, Stephan L.; Cook, Blanche Wiesen.; Corretti, George L.; Dixon, Regina Brave.; Domhoff, G. William.; DuBois, David Graham.; Frappier, Jon.; Freed, Donald, 1932-; Georgakas, Dan.; Katz, Robert.; Kunstler, William M. (William Moses), 1919-1995; Lane, Mark.; Lapity, John.; Lens, Sidney.; Moore, Beverly.; Morgan, Charles.; Oglesby, Carl, 1935-2011; O'Rourke, Maureen.; Rifkin, Jeremy.; Stapleton, Syd.; Stringfellow, William.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Introductory Material
  - Notes on programs and schedule of speakers (Folder 1)
- Who's In Control Teach-In
  The finding aid follows the order of sessions or panels of the teach-in as extracted from the outlines, schedules, and tape labels. The summaries of speaker remarks included in the finding aid came from the "rough outline of speakers" which can be found in the first folder. Sessions generally stretched over two or three tapes. There is usually a small overlap on the continuation tape, though on occasion it appears a small portion of a talk may have been missed. The tapes and derivatives are identified as part 1, 2 or 3 of a session. The scope and content note for each session indicates the part(s) on which each speaker appears. The quoted descriptions of the sessions are taken from notes that accompanied the tapes
  - Assassinations session November 2, 1975
    The Assassinations session (3 original tapes) included four speakers:
    Lee, Marty -- "Introduction outlining the Teach-In's format." (part 1)
    Freed, Donald -- The Assassination of Robert Kennedy (part 1) ("Talks about how the assassinations will spark an awakening")
    Katz, Robert -- Assassination Information Bureau --The Assassination of Martin Luther King (part 1-2) ("Discusses how Martin Luther King's assassination is part of a larger effort to suppress dissent. He reconstructs the killing, pointing out inconsistencies and contradictions.")
    Lane, Mark -- The Assassination of President Kennedy (part 2-3) ("Lane does an outstanding job in attacking the myths proposed by the Warren Commission in the JFK murder. Covers much of the material in his book Rush to Judgement and more.")
    - Part 1, 0566-1-1
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:02:48
        [Restricted]
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-1-1, flash-flv
    - Part 2, 0566-1-2
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:02:02
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-2-2, flash-flv
    - Part 3, 0566-3-3
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 00:48:27
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-3-3, flash-flv
  - Corporate Manipulation session November 3, 1975 10:00 a.m.
    The Corporate Manipulation session consisted of three speakers:
    Domhoff, William -- The Ruling Class (part 1)
    Lens, Sidney -- Labor's Role in Covert War (parts 1 and 2)
    Barnet, Richard -- Multinational Corporations (part 2I)
    - Part 1, 0566-4-1
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:04:47
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-4-1, flash-flv
    - Part 2, 0566-5-2
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 1:04:51
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-5-2, flash-flv
  - Subversion of the Forces of Dissent November 3, 1975, 1:30 p.m.
    The Subversion of the Forces of Dissent panel (3 original tapes) consisted of seven speakers:
    Oglesby, Carl, AIB -- (moderator) (part 1) ("An excellent introduction to this section. Discusses among other things, how the Allies set up ex-Nazis as the new German post-war intelligence community. Also the connections between the federal govt. and organized crime.")
    Stapleton, Syd -- The FBI's Cointelpro and the CIA's Chaos (part 1) ("Former SWPer discusses first-hand how the govt. infiltrated legitimate protest movements. COINTELPRO and Wounded Knee provide the examples of a concerted effort to breakup dissent.")
    Freed, Donald -- Counter-terrorism and the Agent Provocateur (parts 1-2) ("Examples and methods used to kill protest. The connections between Watergate and Patty Hearst. He provides theories on the true nature of the SLA. Ties in the prison system, the CIA and other international criminals.")
    Borman, Nancy, Majority Report -- Subversion of the Women's movement (part 2) ("Documents efforts by the govt. to buy off and subvert the women's movement. Operation Chaos, Mary Jo Cook, Susan Saks and other topics never mentioned in the national media.")
    O'Rourke, Maurine, UM Gay Advocate -- Repression of Gay People (part 2) ("The harassment and oppression of radical lesbians. Kathy Power and Susan Saks, Jill Rayman. A passionate, articulate presentation.")
    [last name not given], Stella -- Repression of Gay People (part 2) ("Attacks homophobia in the New Left and the Teach-In. Relates it to similar experiences with straight academic conferences.")
    DuBois, David, Black Panther -- Conspiracy Against the Black Liberation Movement (part 3) ("DuBois relates his experiences as a Black American living in Black Africa. Relates African liberation struggles to the idea of a world socialist revolution. King, Malcolm X, the Panthers, and bussing are tied in to an overview of racism and imperialism.")
    - Part 1, 0566-6-1
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:03:41
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-6-1, flash-flv
    - Part 2, 0566-7-2
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:02:56
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-7-2, flash-flv
    - Part 3, 0566-8-3
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:03:04
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-8-3, flash-flv
  - Police Repression November 3, 1975, 7:30 p.m
    The session on Police Repression (3 original tapes) seven speakers:
    Kunstler, William -- (moderator) (part 1) ("A short intro. by Kunstler talks about Attica and community control and the repression at Wounded Knee.")
    Butz, Tim -- The Militarization of Police (part1) ("Former intelligence agent thoroughly discusses the intelligence cycle. SLA and SWAT teams. Use of LEAA federal money to bring Viet Nam technology and repression home.")
    Frappier, Jon -- New Police Technology (part 1-2) ("Frappier talks about technology as a tool of repression. LEAA funded police tools. Latin America and Viet Nam. The war comes home.")
    People at the Wheel -- (part 2) ("Music provided by members of the Revolutionary Student Brigade.")
    Kunstler, William -- (part 2) ("Introduction that ties in Viet Nam and the military actions at Wounded Knee.")
    Dixon, Regina Brave -- The Military at Wounded Knee (parts 2-3) ("A first hand account of the US Military actions at Wounded Knee. A fine and complete account.")
    DuBois, David -- Police Repression in Oakland County (part 3) ("A chronological history of the Black Panther Party focusing on Oakland. An excellent overview.")
    - Part 1, 0566-9-1
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 00:18:55
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-9-1, flash-flv
    - Part 2, 0566-10-2
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:02:55
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-10-2, flash-flv
    - Part 3, 0566-11-3
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:03:50
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-11-3, flash-flv
    - Part 4, 0566-12-4
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:04:03
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-12-4, flash-flv
  - Surveillance & Dataveillance November 3, 1975, 10:00 a.m.
    The panel titled Surveillance & Dataveillance consisted of three speakers:
    Lapity, Jon -- (part 1)
    Corsetti, George -- (part 1) ("He documents specifics of police surveillance and infiltration of various Mich. area groups. The maintaining of files, informers and dirty tricks.")
    Morgan, Chuck, ACLU -- Electronic Surveillance Systems and Computer Data (p 2) ("A speech everyone should hear. He outlines the use of satellites, computers, voiceprints, wire-tapping. The CIA, Dept. of Defense, the NSA. An Orwellian nightmare. Very good question and answer period follows.")
    - Part 1, 0566-13-1
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:03:09
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-13-1, flash-flv
    - Part 2, 0566-14-2
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:02:58
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-14-2, flash-flv
  - Mind Control November 4, 1975, 1:30 p.m.
    The Mind Control session (3 original tapes) included six speakers:
    Cook, Blanch -- The Garrison State and Mind Control (part 1-2) ("A chilling account of weather warfare, psychosurgery and behavior modification. Funds provided by LEAA in some cases.")
    Georgakas, Dan -- Behavior Modification in Prisons (part 2) ("Revealing accounts of behavior mod and drugs used in prisons. Hurricane Carter and Martin Sostre cases are reviewed. Lobotomies and the Nuremberg principles. A subject no one can ignore.")
    Freed, Donald -- (part 2) ("The links between behavior mod-brainwashing and Sirhan Sirhan. Explores use of Clockwork Orange techniques in political frameworks. Programmed assassins.")
    Chorover, Steve -- Behavior Modification from Genesis to Genocide (part 2) ("Discusses the theoretical implications of behavior modification and mass control. Relates it all to the rise of Nazism.")
    Burroughs, William -- (part 2) ("A speech on control by this infamous poet you just have to hear for yourself.")
    Moore, Beverly -- Content Analysis of T.V. Commercials (part 3) ("This young lawyer from Nader talks about the lack of information in T.V. commercials. Touches on the vast amount of data supplied through such an innocent medium and its potential for abuse.")
    - Part 1, 0566-15-1
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:02:51
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-15-1, flash-flv
    - Part 2, 0566-16-2
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:03:04
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-16-2, flash-flv
  - Looking Towards the Future November 4, 1975, 7:30 p.m.
    The closing session of the Teach-In was titled "Looking Towards the Future" and included three speakers:
    Stringfellow, William; Lawyer an theologian -- (part 1)
    Rifkin, Jeremy, People's Bicentennial Commission -- The American Revolution: A Two-hundred Year Cover-up (part1) ("A high spirited look at the history of 'free enterprise' in America. Economic democracy and worker control. A timely tape that will counter all the rest of the 1776 bull shit around.")
    Ahmad, Eqbal; Pasktani born journalist and antiwar activist -- Revolution in the Third-world (part 2-3) ("A closing to the Teach-In that is spiritual in the deepest sense of the word. A free-flowing rap that ties in all the material covered giving hope and strength to all in the struggle.")
    Criley, Richard; - ACLU -- Tape ends with presentation by Richard Criley, American Civil Liberties Union, on press freedom, civil liberties and Nixon/Ford administrations crime bills "Senate Bill 1400" and "Senate Bill 1." Pakistani-born journalist Eqbal Ahmed closes the conference. The end of Eqbal Ahmad's talk appears to have been taped over part of another session.
    (There is some extraneous footage at the beginning of tapes 2 and 3.)
    - Part 1, 0566-17-1
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:00:03
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-17-1, flash-flv
    - Part 2, 0566-18-2
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:01:26
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-18-2, flash-flv
    - Part 3, 0566-19-3
      - Original:, open reel videotape, b/w, sound, 01:03:16
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 0566-19-3, flash-flv